<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<article>
  <metaData docId="0">
    <parseTime>2018-03-29T11:34:07</parseTime>
    <fileName>yadav-2011.pdf</fileName>
    <filePath>upload-dir/yadav-2011.xml</filePath>
    <title>A Framework For Authorship Identification Of Questioned Documents Forensic And Linguistic Convergence</title>
    <authors>Admin</authors>
    <refCount>0</refCount>
    <publicationDate>January 2011</publicationDate>
  </metaData>
  <textElements>
    <abstract><![CDATA[ any questioned document examination in india is limited in its scope of authorship identification when the investigators are unable to obtain the criminals standard handwriting specimen every person s style of handwriting is unique and has its own personalized touch it is because of this reason that handwriting is very difficult to disguise and forge making handwriting analysis an effective tool for incriminating a suspect the application of linguistic tools such as stylistics can support forensic techniques in eliminating this limitation using three types of writing style features such as lexical syntactic and structural features we have attempted to develop a framework for authorship identification by analyzing these features in the questioned text as well as comparing its results with those of known authors based on forensic handwriting principles this study will help in not only authorship identification but will exclusively help in linking the criminals motive mens rea guilty]]></abstract>
    <fullText><![CDATA[1 
 
 
MJAL 3:1 Winter 2011                                                                     ISSN 0974-8741 
A Framework for Authorship Identification of Questioned Documents: Forensic and Linguistic 
Convergence by Sresha Yadav  and  Smita Jha   
 
A Framework for Authorship Identification of Questioned Documents: 
Forensic and Linguistic Convergence 
 
                              
                                   Sresha Yadav * and  Smita Jha ** 
                             
 
*Research Scholar, Department of Humanities & Social Sciences Studies, Indian 
Institute of Technology, Roorkee-247667, India, E-mail: sresha85@gmail.com 
 
**Assistant Professor, Department of Humanities & Social Sciences Studies, Indian 
Institute of Technology, Roorkee-247667, India, E-mail: smitaiitr@gmail.com 
 
 
Abstract 
  
Any questioned document examination in India is limited in its scope of authorship 
identification when the investigators are unable to obtain the criminal’s standard 
handwriting specimen. Every person's style of handwriting is unique and has its own 
personalized touch. It is because of this reason that handwriting is very difficult to 
disguise and forge, making handwriting analysis an effective tool for incriminating a 
suspect. The application of linguistic tools such as stylistics can support Forensic 
techniques in eliminating this limitation. Using three types of writing style features such 
as lexical, syntactic, and structural features, we have attempted to develop a framework 
for authorship identification by analyzing these features in the questioned text as well as 
comparing its results with those of known authors based on forensic handwriting 
principles. This study will help in not only authorship identification but will exclusively 
help in linking the criminal’s motive (mens rea- guilty mind) with the evidence and 
crime. Therefore, this study uses a convergence framework using forensic and linguistic 
techniques for authorship identification. 
Keywords: Questioned document, Linguistics, Forensic handwriting principles 
 
2 
 
 
MJAL 3:1 Winter 2011                                                                     ISSN 0974-8741 
A Framework for Authorship Identification of Questioned Documents: Forensic and Linguistic 
Convergence by Sresha Yadav  and  Smita Jha   
 
 
Introduction 
In the present scenario with the emergence of new and sophisticated technologies, crime 
in India has taken a new ramped. In the field of Questioned Document examination, 
investigating personnel’s sometimes faced problems due to the non-availability of 
standard specimens from the suspects of crime. Thus, one of the major challenges in front 
of the law enforcement agencies is to develop an investigative tool which in addition to 
the traditional approach of authorship identification also increases the effectiveness of the 
identification procedure. Application of linguistic techniques for authorship identification 
will augment the efficacy of examination procedure even if the availability of standard 
samples is limited or nil. To fix the authorship of any Questioned Document is important 
in the context of ‘white collar crimes” i.e. crime involving forgery, identity thefts, 
counterfeiting, anonymous letters such as threatening or suicide note. The examination of 
these types of documents is vital because they are produced directly in the court of law as 
a connecting link between the perpetrator and the committed crime.  For the analysis of a 
these type of documents , it is important to study the written language of the perpetrator,  
as the vocabulary usage in the text may yield “signature” words unique to the 
offender(Douglas et al, 1986). 
 
    Handwriting Analysis and Authorship Identification 
 In India, traditional approach of handwriting analysis is been employed for authorship 
identification. The process involves extracting certain characteristic features present in a 
text to determine the authorship (Zheng et al, 2006). Class and individualistic 
characteristics are used for this purpose of examination. On the basis of handwriting 
principles, these characteristics are determined when compared to standard specimens 
obtained from the suspect. The main principles of handwriting analysis is based on 
presumed facts that the writing of every individual is personal to self only , two different 
persons can’t write in similar manner, presence of natural variations in writings of a same 
3 
 
 
MJAL 3:1 Winter 2011                                                                     ISSN 0974-8741 
A Framework for Authorship Identification of Questioned Documents: Forensic and Linguistic 
Convergence by Sresha Yadav  and  Smita Jha   
 
person, disguised writing always lead to inferior quality of writing  and writing of every 
individual is a response to brain stimuli so it is a kind of brain writing which is  an 
acquired skill and helps to determine the individuality of the person through writing 
features. The writing practices we learn during our time at school are very difficult to 
lose, as we get used to the particular way that we hold a pen, shape the letters we write 
and how we space our words and lines. These are some of the factors that prove useful 
during the analysis of a document. Investigators analyze these aspects of suspicious 
documents i.e the printing style, paper and ink, all of which help to identify a forged 
letter. The handwriting section of forensic science involves the comparing and 
authentication of written documents such as ransom notes, forged contracts, forged wills, 
fake ID's and passports and any other form of writing or printed material. The analysis of 
someone's handwriting is most commonly used to prove that two documents were written 
by the same person. When looking at a person's handwriting, the examiners usually look 
for personalized characteristics under four areas including line quality, form, content and 
arrangement. The form of writing involves examining the shape of singular letters and 
identifying if the slant is in a certain direction, the size and how they are connected with 
the next letter. Unusual characteristics, such as the use of a plus sign or the ampersand 
(&) are also noted. Examining the content of written and printed papers is done to 
identify similarities between punctuation, spelling, grammar, vocabulary and paragraph 
phrasing. 
Document examiners compare unidentified documents with a 'standard', a sample from a 
suspect. A standard is usually produced by the suspect under supervision. Even under 
supervision, the suspect still has the chance to disguise their handwriting, which is why 
investigators then have to collect other standards of casual handwriting from a suspect. 
The casual handwriting is undisguised and can therefore be compared with the unknown 
sample either with words that match or letter-by-letter.  
    
4 
 
 
MJAL 3:1 Winter 2011                                                                     ISSN 0974-8741 
A Framework for Authorship Identification of Questioned Documents: Forensic and Linguistic 
Convergence by Sresha Yadav  and  Smita Jha   
 
    Scope of Linguistics in Authorship Identification 
 The language used in the questioned text is of great importance because each and every 
individual possesses certain characteristic features which will help to identify the 
geographical origin, age, occupation, sex, education, and religious background by the 
study of the language used in the text. The study by Koppel, Argamon, and Shimoni 
(2002) provided evidence for the fact that how the language used by male and female 
study group varies with respect to the use of pronouns. Corney, Vel, Anderson, and 
Mohay (2002) points out that how the educational background of any person is reflected 
in the language which is used by the person. In recent years many researchers explored 
the area of authorship identification in electronic messages and proposed different 
classification techniques with multidisciplinary approach to identify the author of the 
unknown text with greater accuracy. The main problem in any questioned text is the 
factor of anonymity, the individual tried to refrain the basic identity information i.e. 
gender, age, occupation etc (Zheng et al, 2006). The importance of the linguistic analysis 
in the examination of the questioned text provides information with respect to suspect 
age, gender, race, occupation, and educational background even if the availability of the 
standard writing specimen is limited or nil. Application of linguistics tools also extends 
the principles of psycholinguistics techniques to sketch the offender profile which can be 
used to identify anonymous letters writers (Casey Owens, 1984) and any person who 
make written or spoken threats of violence (Miron and Douglas, 1979). The field of 
psycholinguistics is concerned with the relationship between linguistics and the 
psychological processes underlying the. Linguistic features also help in linking the 
individual motive (mens rea- guilty mind) by analyzing character styles and personality 
traits to understand or to predict criminal behavior  
 
Methodology 
The main purpose of this study is to develop a framework utilizing the techniques of 
linguistics and forensics which not only helps in authorship identification but also to 
5 
 
 
MJAL 3:1 Winter 2011                                                                     ISSN 0974-8741 
A Framework for Authorship Identification of Questioned Documents: Forensic and Linguistic 
Convergence by Sresha Yadav  and  Smita Jha   
 
establish the criminal motive.  On the basis of handwriting analysis individual 
characteristics i.e. size of the letters, arrangement, spacing between the letters, words and 
lines, pen pause, pen lift, hesitation and connecting strokes; class characteristics i. e. 
pictorial effect, style, movement of writing, writing speed, alignment of letters, and line 
quality of the written text is to be determined and compared with the results obtained 
from linguistic analysis. Based on the review of earlier related studies and analysis of the 
questioned text of written document or computer generated document, we considered 
three types of linguistic feature set: lexical, syntactic and structural features. 
In this study we included lexical feature used in de Vel (2000), vocabulary richness(Yule, 
1938); syntactic features, including  function words ( Mosteller and Wallace, 1964), part 
of speech incorporation (Stamatatos et al,2001), punctuation characteristics ( Baayen et 
al., 2002) . The structural features represent the writes style of organizing the layout of 
writing text (Zheng, 2006). 
 
 
 
Figure I. Framework proposed for Authorship Identification  
  
 
Step-2 
Step -1  
 Features extraction 
Pre examination 
Collection  
Step -4 
Step - 3 
Analysis and comparison 
Syntactic 
features 
 
 
Individual 
characteristics  
Structural 
features 
 
Lexical features Class 
characteristics 
     Linguistics analysis   Handwriting examination 
Questioned document 
      Authorship identification 
6 
 
 
MJAL 3:1 Winter 2011                                                                     ISSN 0974-8741 
A Framework for Authorship Identification of Questioned Documents: Forensic and Linguistic 
Convergence by Sresha Yadav  and  Smita Jha   
 
Conclusion and Future Challenges 
In this present study, we proposed a framework for authorship identification of 
questioned text by adopting the linguistic as well as forensic approaches and techniques. 
We believed that the proposed framework has the potential to assist in authorship 
identification and also to sketch the linguistic behaviour profile of the suspect. As this 
study is in nascent phase its use and applicability in the Indian court of law is far beyond 
admissibility. To validate the proposed framework would be another challenging task for 
the future researchers so that the technique can be truly useful for assisting the examiners 
for identity tracing of the unknown suspect. 
 
 
References  
 
Baayen, R.H., Van Halteren, H., Neijit, A., & Tweedie, F. 2002. An experiment in 
authorship attribution.  In proceedings of the 6th International conference on the 
Statistical Analysis of Textual Data, St. Malo, France. 
 
Corney, M., Vel, O. d., Anderson, A. and Mohay, G. 2002.Gender-Preferential Text 
Mining of Email Discourse. In proceedings of the 18th Annual Computer Security 
Application Conference, LA, NV 
 
Douglas et al. “Criminal Profiling from Crime Scene Analysis”.Behavioural sciences & 
the law 4.4(1986): 401-421. 
 
Koppel et al. “Automatically categorizing written text by author gender”. Literary and 
linguistic computing 17.4(2002): 401-412. 
 
Mosteller, F et al. 1964. Interference and disputer authorship: The Federalist. Reading, 
MA: Addison – Wesley  
 
Stamatatos et al. “Computer based authorship attribution without lexical measures”. 
Computers and the humanities 35.2(2001): 193-214. 
 
Yule, G.U. “On sentence as a statistical characteristic of style in prose”. Biometrica 30 
(1938): 363-390. 
 
7 
 
 
MJAL 3:1 Winter 2011                                                                     ISSN 0974-8741 
A Framework for Authorship Identification of Questioned Documents: Forensic and Linguistic 
Convergence by Sresha Yadav  and  Smita Jha   
 
Zheng, R., Li, J., Chen, H., and Huang, Z. “A Framework for Authorship Identification of 
Online Messages: Writing- Style Features and Classification Techniques”. The American 
society for information science and technology, 57.3(2006): 378-393. 
]]></fullText>
  </textElements>
</article>
